Time to look at some operators.
Now what operators?
You know them?
You did math at school.
Plus?
Minus.
What was that thing called?
Bodmas.
Brackets of divide.
Yeah.
You thought those things were no value?
Of course they have value.
As you know, when you got to pull out the calculator and work out, you know how much a tip you've
got to give someone or whatever.
You're using operators.
And the same thing applies in our programming.
And there are a range of exactly the same operators in some little special ones that just make life
a little bit easier.
So we've got plus very simple.
If I want to take a plus B equals 30 okay.
It's as simple as anything.
You understand subtraction.
So that's just the little hyphen.
The little dash is our subtraction.
Multiplication in programming is not an X, it's the asterisk or the star.
So that is a symbol we use for multiplying two values together.
Division is a forward slash not a back.
Be careful of that.
It must be a forward slash.
That's what we use for division And moving down.
There's a little special one here.
It's this sort of a percent sign, and it's what's called a modulus.
It's exactly the same as division.
The only difference is it gives you as the answer what was the remainder.
So for example, if I had four divided by five divided by two and I used it as a division, you would
get the answer of five divided by two goes in twice.
So you've got two point whatever remainder.
If I did modulus and I put five and percentage sign two, it would say well two goes into five twice.
That's two remainder one.
And so the answer would be the remainder portion just one.
So that's what modulus is.
And we may pick up that a little bit later where you see you use it.
But it's not that important at the moment.
Exponent.
That's when something is to the power of something.
So 110 to the power of two.
Then it will be a ten star.
Star two.
And finally, you've got this thing which is called a floor division.
And basically all it's doing is it's rounding off something.
So we say nine forward slash forward slash two.
Instead of giving you four point something it's just giving you the four.
So it's not giving you any of the the remaining parts.
It's giving you an integer.
So those are the basic operators.
So those are very cool operators.
And let's see how we can actually use those.
Okay.
So let's start off with the easy one.
Let's create a variable that is going to store a number.
But actually we're going to make this one this variable a bit more interesting.
We're not just going to store five I want to store five plus two.
So now inside this variable maanum it's actually at first the first thing it's going to do is it's going
to add five plus two which is seven.
And then it's going to take the value seven and store that in maanum.
So it's not storing this whole expression.
Instead the first thing when the program runs.
What it does is it takes five plus two.
Okay.
That's equal to seven.
And then it goes Marnham is now equal to seven as compared to if we put.
What do you think would happen if we put two little strings around there.
You know, inverted commas.
That would be a totally different thing then it would actually be storing five plus two the actual expression
in there.
So if we put my num and ran that you're going to see printed out at the bottom over here, it's got
five plus two.
But if we remove that and then look down to the bottom of your screen, you'll see it is got seven.
So let's actually make this print statement a little bit more exciting because say we were running this
program and we ran it and we and it came and it printed seven.
That doesn't really tell you much.
It doesn't even tell you that what you're really trying to work out is five plus two.
So in order to actually tell the person who's reading your output of your program what you were trying
to do, what you can do is you can add more than one element to your print statement.
Okay.
So what I'm now going to do is I'm actually going to first print out a string that says five plus two
is equal to.
And then I'm going to put a comma and print out the variable.
So basically what the comma is doing is it's telling your it's telling wing or Python that you're wanting
to print two different things but put them together, put them together in one print statement.
So I run it on it and hopefully make more sense.
You see at the bottom five plus two equals seven.
Actually this is a type of what is called concatenation.
Uh, we it's where you're putting two things and adding them together, where you're adding a string
and something together.
So that's a fancy word.
You can add it to your other fancy words that you've already learned.
Um, so it's just simply taking two things.
In this case, it's taking a string, uh, variable or a string variable number, an integer variable,
and printing it alongside a piece of text or a string.
And you can concatenate like, as many things as you want into this print statement.
So I could say I want to put some exclamation marks.
It's now going to print the string five plus two, then the variable, my number, and then my another
string, which has got a whole lot of exclamation marks.
Okay, so that was addition with integers.
Again you can add two floats if you would like.
And that's just the same thing.
Addition is always going to do the same thing it's going to add.
Or obviously this is no longer five plus two because it's now doing 5.1 plus 2.1.
But anyways, basically what I'm trying to say is you can add two integers, you can add two floats.
It's just addition normal addition as you would do math.
Okay.
We're then going to I mean subtraction division.
It's all pretty self-explanatory.
If we put a minus in there it's going to print five minus two if you remember what the division sign
was.
It was this forward slash.
It's now going five divided by two.
And then if you are really clever maybe you remember what the this thing called floor division did.
It basically took away the five and is just printing the two.
So it's basically converting that float which it should print 2.55 divided by two.
This now just prints the integer.
So just basically delete everything after the decimal place.
What about that modulus one.
I'll show you what the modulus one did if you okay.
So like we were explaining earlier it prints what's left.
So obviously two is going into five two times.
Like my dad explained earlier.
So two twos are four remainder left with one.
And so if we change this to let's just say nine, that's also going to print one.
Excellent.
What a great example that was.
How about five.
Okay.
We can do that father work.
Excellent.
Five goes into nine once.
Remainder four okay.
And what about we didn't do multiply.
Can you remember?
Do you remember what the multiply sign is?
You thought it was there?
No, it's not that.
It's that.
Okay, nine times five.
Did you work that out before you looked?
Hopefully they worked it out.
Okay.
Now, the fun thing with, uh, operators is that with maths, obviously operators, you're just using
it with numbers.
But in programming you can actually use it with strings as well.
So let's create a string.
Let's make it our favorite color okay.
So for example my favorite color is blue.
Now instead of just saying blue I want to add something to it.
So with strings you can only add strings to strings and integers to integers or integers.
So basically you can only add a string to a string, and you can only add a number to a number.
So you can't mix.
When you work with data types you can't mix them together.
They don't like it.
They get very upset.
So if we want to add two strings together, well, they've got to both be strings.
If you try and add a integer a number to a string.
It's not going to go down well.
Okay.
So now I'm going to print this string concatenated string called mastering.
And it's going to just print that sentence.
But what you do notice here is when you use this addition it doesn't put in this space.
It's basically just taking what you wrote there and adding what you wrote there straight to the end
of what's before it.
One thing that you should, uh, one thing that I should tell you with, uh, adding strings is it's
no longer called addition.
It's now called concatenation.
So this is actually called concatenating two strings together.
But obviously this what I've done here doesn't really make sense because I've just I could have just
put that all inside the first string.
So let's just say I want to make, uh, let's call it mastering one.
And I want to now call this my favorite color.
And now instead of printing putting those two together in the first one, I've now put them in their
own separate variables, and I'm now going to concatenate them in the print statement like I showed
you before.
Okay.
Now here again, you'll notice it doesn't put in that space for you.
So if you want a space, it's pretty simple.
You just put in your own one.
Obviously a space is just a string with.
I've just clicked the spacebar there and added it between them and printed it again.
And now I have it in a more correct looking sentence.
So essentially what we've done is we have added together two variables that we've created my string
and my string, one which are both string variables.
And we've created a piece of text, a piece of string that we are adding as part of that.
So as long as these are all the same thing, uh, where it's going to get upset is if you start to mix
things up, uh, now we are trying to add what is not a string to a string.
That is an integer.
Down here you'll see top error.
Not very happy with what you've done.
Bad thing.
Don't do it.
This is not a string.
Must be a string.
It even tells you there.
So keep the same data types together and life will be happy.
So with strings, all you can actually do is addition, which we said was called concatenation.
You can't subtract or multiply or divide because that doesn't really make sense.
What is my favorite color?
Like that doesn't make sense.
Okay, so with strings you can use addition.
With numbers you can go wild and use any of those different operators.
Okay.
So before where we showed you here, um, trying to add this number nine to a string you saw we got
an error.
So again, obviously if well, maybe not obviously, but if we had made this an integer instead or a
number, let's just call it my int and call.
Let's just say it's equal to 14.
And now in this print statement if we now went Ma int plus five and decided to print that, it's not
going to give us an error because Python has realized this value.
Here is a number.
This value here that we are adding with is a number.
So yes, I can do this.
But if this change to my string like we saw before, it's now evaluated this first thing as blue.
But we have defined it as up here.
And the second one it's evaluated as integer or as a number.
So it's now told us how can I add a string to a number.
That's impossible.
And it will give us an error.
Right.
So that is a brief introduction to the various operators.
We're going to be using them a lot.
You're going to get quite familiar with them as we go forward.
But as you see they're not that difficult.
It's not that dissimilar to what you would have learned just in your mathematics back at school.
So that's operators and have some fun.
Just play around with them.
And as long as you keep your operators all in the same time, life will be good.